<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A faithfull report of proceedings anent the assemblie of ministers at Abirdeen vpon Twesday 2. Iuly 1605</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19872</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 63</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113262</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848499</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848499</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13597</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19872)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13597)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 641:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A faithfull report of proceedings anent the assemblie of ministers at Abirdeen vpon Twesday 2. Iuly 1605</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Schilders],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>21 Februar. 1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 22053.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="sco">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13597:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13597:1"/>
            <p>A faithfull Report of proceedings anent the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie of Miniſters at <hi>Abir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen</hi> vpon Tweſday 2. Iuly 1605.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Proverb. 18. verſ. 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that is first in his owne cauſe is iust, then cometh his neighbour and maketh inquirie of him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>21. Februar. 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13597:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13597:2"/>
            <head>A faithfull Report of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings anent the Aſſemblie of Miniſters at <hi>Abirdeen</hi> vpon Tweſday the ſecond of Iulij 1605.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I haue been in <hi>England</hi> many yeeres, yet I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but be moved with the grievous traducing of faithfull Miniſters in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which I heare euery day as I haue occaſion to meet with men ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther addicted (more or leſſe) to Papiſtrie, or vtterly ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Scottiſ-affairs. Traducing, I ſaye, ſic Miniſters as if they were indeed guiltie of high treaſon. A lively member of the Kirk cannot but be ſenſible of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles thereof, in what part of the world ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:13597:3"/> he be: How then can I be vnmoued to heare ſic things of the principal members of the Kirk in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo neare and deare not only to Scottiſ-me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to Engliſh-men too, if they be truely religious? For doeth not euery wiſe-hearted Chriſtian evidently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that (among other Stratagemes of this declining age) Satan would blemiſh the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell and vnderminde the Kirk, through the ſides of thoſe faithfull Miniſters.</p>
            <p>I haue thought it therefore very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to collect and ſet donn this faithfull <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> hoping that th'indifferent Reader will ſuſpend his iudgement, till <hi>Trueth (Times daughter)</hi> be fit <hi>to ſhew her ſelfe in publict.</hi> I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute no obiections, becauſe I would not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend: and beſides <hi>Rectum est index ſui &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liqui.</hi> Laſtly I call this <hi>Report faithfull,</hi> becauſe I haue faithfullie collected the ſame out of faithfull intelligences ſent out of <hi>Scotlande</hi> from faithfull Brethren; and not becauſe I can ovow (though I beleeve) everie part thereof to be vndoubtedly true. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pray with proteſtation that this Report
<pb facs="tcp:13597:3"/> be not preiudiciall to a more evident truth, which hereafter may bee publiſhed by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie; or by the Miniſtrie.</p>
            <p>In the Generall Aſſembly at <hi>Halyrude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hous,</hi> in <hi>November</hi> 1602. the Brethren con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to his Ma: that the next Aſſemblie ſould be at <hi>Abirdeen</hi> the laſt <hi>Tweſday</hi> of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 1604. and not before (Notwithſtanding it was then and there ordained with his Ma. conſent, that the diets of Aſſemblies be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and kept preciſely euerie yeere ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to an act of Parliament 1592) Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting his Ma. pleaſure ſo much, as that they did not duly conſider how preiudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all it might proove to the libertie of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rk, to tranſgreſſe the ſaid Actes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Generall Aſſembly, in not hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancie the Generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <hi>Once</hi> (at leaſt) euery yeere.</p>
            <p>That their exceeding regard of his Ma: pleaſure may ȝit more appeare, it is not to be forgotten, that the Preſbyteries yeelded to a Letter dated at <hi>Perth 4. Iuly</hi> 1604. and ſubſcribed be the Laird of <hi>Lowreston</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:13597:4"/> Kings Commiſſioner, <hi>Maister Patrik Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loway,</hi> Moderator of the ſaid Aſſemblie at <hi>Holyrudehous</hi> and Maiſter <hi>Richard Thomeſon,</hi> Clerk to the Commiſſioners, in name of the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly: Whereby they were certified that it was his Maieſties pleaſure that the Aſſembly ſould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued to the <hi>First Tweſday of Iuly</hi> 1605. if advertiſement came not ſooner. And this they did, notwithſtanding an Act of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly at <hi>Holyrudehous,</hi> whereby all power was taken from the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly, to make any alteration, drift or delay of the diet of the Generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly: Which act was made with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties conſent, to remooue a iuſt conceyued grief of the Kirk.</p>
            <p>The Generall Aſſembly being ſo mani-yeeres deferred, open ſcandalls ſo multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the rather becauſe inferior Iudicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were contemned by the chiefeſt male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, who did elude, and eſcape their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures by appellation to a Generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, which they neuer expected; and Papiſts
<pb facs="tcp:13597:4"/> grew ſo inſolent, Ieſuites and Seminarie Prieſtes travayling ſecurely within the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, That of neceſſitie many Synodes and Presbyteries vſed many meanes and Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, yea many Commiſſioners from many Provinces, convening at <hi>Saint Iohnstone</hi> in <hi>October</hi> 1604. made (with conſent of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Commiſſioner) a Supplication to his Maieſtie, for haſting the General Aſſembly; But all to no great purpoſe.</p>
            <p>For not long before the vttermoſt day of Aſſembly were letters dated at <hi>Edingburgh,</hi> ſubſcribed as thoſe from <hi>Perth,</hi> and directed to the Presbyteries, adviſing them not to keepe the fifth day of Iulij: Which error of naming the fifth day for the <hi>First Tweſday,</hi> which was the <hi>ſecond</hi> day of <hi>Iuli</hi> directly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in the ſaid letters from <hi>Perth,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were of purpoſe or no, it is not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. But ſo it was that the Commiſſioners of ſome Presbyteries by reaſon therof came not to <hi>Abirdeen</hi> till the 4. and 5. dayes of <hi>Iuli,</hi> and ſome not at all.</p>
            <p>The cauſes mooving the Presbyteries to
<pb facs="tcp:13597:5"/> ſend their Commiſſioners (theſe letters not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding) were theſe. 1. They came too late. 2. They were not with command, but by way of advice. 3. By the ſaid Act at <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyrudehous,</hi> the power of altering or delaying the Diet of Aſſemblies was taken from the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſemblie. 4 No other day and place were appointed. 5. The danger of the forfalting the libertie of the Kirk, and 6. The neceſſitie of an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters who convened at <hi>Abir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> of <hi>Iuly</hi> were theſe, <hi>Maist. Iohn Forbes, Ma. Iohn Munro, Ma. Andro Duncan, Ma. Alexander Stranchen, Ma. William Forbes, Ma. Robert ȝoungſon, Ma. Iames Irving, Ma. Charles Ferme, Ma. Iohn Sharp, Ma. Robert Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Ma. Archibald Blackburne, Ma. Iames Roſſe, Ma. Dauid Rail, Ma. Alexander Strogie, M. Iames Mill, Ma. David Robertſon, Ma. William Dauidſon, Ma. Robert Reed, and Iohn Rough, in all 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the ſermon made by Ma. <hi>Iames Roſſe</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Abirdeen,</hi> the Brethren convened
<pb facs="tcp:13597:5"/> in the Kirk with the Laird of <hi>Lowreston,</hi> &amp; by mutuall conſent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued their donn ſitting till the after noone in expectation of mo Brethren hindred in their iourney, as was ſuppoſed, by iniurie of weather. At twoo houres in the after noone they mett in the <hi>Seſsion-houſe,</hi> within the Kirk of <hi>Abirdeen,</hi> and after incalling on the name of God by Mai. <hi>Dauid Rout</hi> Moderator of the Synod of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birdeen,</hi> in place of M. <hi>Pal. Galloway,</hi> they ſent for the ordinarie Clerk of the Aſſemblie, who went to them; At which time the Laird of <hi>Lowreston</hi> ſitting don amongſt them, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: <hi>That though he might charge them, yet he would rather make vſe of a miſsive Letter from the Lordes of the ſecret Councell, directed to the Ministerie in their Aſſembly at Abirdeen,</hi> which he deſired them to read and anſwer. But vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till a Moderator was choſen, that could not be. He named Maiſter <hi>Iohn Forbes</hi> to be the mouth for the reſt; But perceiuing that the Aſſembly would proceed orderly in their election, he remooved him ſelfe of his owne free will, That (as he openly declared) hee
<pb facs="tcp:13597:6"/> might eſchew to be quarelled &amp; found fault with, for ſeeming to approove the ſaid Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by his preſence, if it ſould fall out that he and they ſould not agree. After his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooving, they deſired Ma. <hi>Thomas Nichol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone</hi> (ordinarie Clerke to the Aſſembly) to remaine with them, and to do his office, He refuſed til he ſould ſee how the iſſue of their doings ſould content the Laird of <hi>Lowre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> and ſo (but firſt deſiring and obtayning diſpenſation for his abſence) he likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooved himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The Aſſembly proceedes, &amp; having put in lytes Maiſter <hi>Robert Durie,</hi> Ma. <hi>Iohn Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> and Ma. <hi>Iohn Forbes,</hi> who were in ele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with generall conſent chooſe Mai. <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Forbes</hi> Moderator, and the rather, becauſe they were willing to reſpect the Laird of <hi>Lowſtones</hi> nominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; and after prayer made by the new Moderator, they did chooſe M. <hi>Iohn Sharp</hi> Clerk for that time.</p>
            <p>After this election the Letter miſſiue was read, and the iudgement of the Aſſemblie craved. The letter conſiſted of two pointes;
<pb facs="tcp:13597:6"/> firſt that the Aſſembly ſould be preſently diſſolved; and ſecondly, that no new diet ſould be appointed till his Maieſtie were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted therewith. And yet it was agreed betweene the Lord <hi>Chancellor</hi> and Mai. <hi>Iohn Forbes</hi> in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> before the Miniſters met in their Aſſembly at <hi>Abirdeen,</hi> that the Miniſters ſould meet, and (vpon requeſt of the Councell) having fenced their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, continue the intreating of all things to a new day. The Aſſembly yeelded to the former, But for reaſons before mentioned, thought it needfull to appoint a new diet, if the Laird of <hi>Lowreston</hi> would not, but if he would they agreed to conſent thereto, were the day appointed long or ſhort. They ſent &amp; deſired his preſence. The Moderator de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to him the iudgement of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, &amp; he approved the former part of their concluſion, but refuſed to deſigne any time long or ſhort, Albeit the Aſſembly aſſured him that vpon the reverent reſpect they had to ſatisfie his Ma. deſire, they would bee als readie afterward to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue to a certen day,
<pb facs="tcp:13597:7"/> if his Ma. ſould require the ſame. After long reaſoning was brought to conſider the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of continuing the Aſſembly to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine time: and the rather, becauſe (as hee him ſelfe did there openly report) it was thought they ſould never haue Aſſembly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: but yet would not agree therevnto, becauſe (as he affirmed) he had no warrant ſo to do. He therefore againe did volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily remooue him ſelfe, though he was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſtay, giving the ſecond time the ſame cauſe of ſic remooving him ſelfe, which hee gaue before.</p>
            <p>Preſently after, The intreating of the affairs of the Aſſembly were continued to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tweſday of September</hi> then next following a <hi>Abirdeen;</hi> &amp; intimation ordained to be made in all Presbyteries according to the order &amp; cuſtome obſerved in ſic caſes. Which being done, &amp; the Aſſembly readie to diſſolue, the Laird of <hi>Lawreston</hi> returned of him ſelfe (for the doores were neuer ſhut) and proteſted that he did not acknowledge their meeting for a lawfull Aſſemblie from the beginning;
<pb facs="tcp:13597:7"/> Becauſe of the abſence of M. <hi>Patrik Galloway,</hi> Moderator of the former general Aſſembly; &amp; of the ordinary clerk: (Here it is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the number of Miniſters aſſembled, was not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excepted againſt.) To the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Moderator (in name of the reſt) an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that the reaſons thereof notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, it behoved the Aſſembly to be lawful: Becauſe of the warrant. 1. of Gods word. 2. Lawes of the Realme. 3. continuall prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Kirk, ſince the yeere of our Lord 1560. But moſt clearly ſet donn in the book of diſcipline eſtabliſhed in this Lande, at his Ma. owne deſire publickly made to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at <hi>Glaſgo,</hi> 1581. where n the 7. ca. art. 3. &amp; 4. it is thus written: <hi>All ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiasticall Aſſemblies haue power to convene to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for treating of things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the church p rtaining to their charges. They haue power to ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>point times and places to that effect, &amp; one Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to appoint diet, time and place of another.</hi> 4. The ſubſcription and oath of the King and all his ſubiects. 5. The ſaid letter of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners from <hi>Perth</hi> and. 6. Preſidents in
<pb facs="tcp:13597:8"/> the Regiſter of the Aſſembly of chooſing a new Moderator in abſence of the old, and a clerke for the time in place of th'ordinarie.</p>
            <p>In meane time the Lord of <hi>Lowreſton</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Iohn Wiſheart</hi> meſſinger to charge the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly with letters of Horning to ſuffer the ſame to deſert, and gave a ſubſcribed copie to the Moderator in name of the Aſſembly? The reaſons whereof were theſe. 1. That his Ma. had ſignified that he could not be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved anent a general Aſſembly till the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was paſt. 2. That this Aſſembly was without his knowledge &amp; conſent. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto Obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was given inſtantly, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator craving a certificat of the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hand of the meſſinger, who was alſo a publike Notarie: but he refuſing, The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters after the diſſolving of the Aſſemblie with prayer by the Moderator, went pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſently to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Clerkes chamber of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birdeen,</hi> &amp; tooke inſtruments of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the ſaid charge: Which was t'honly charge that ever they heard of firſt or laſt by publick or private intimation or knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:13597:8"/> whatſoever, as they proteſted vpon their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in their Apologie ſend afterward to his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Of this charge no mention was made to the Lords of the ſecret Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, but another was alleadged to haue ben giuen by vertue of the ſame letters on <hi>Monday the first of Iuly</hi> by open proclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the mercat croſſe of <hi>Abirdeen.</hi> Whereas (in trueth) there was no ſic thing don. For then the Laird of <hi>Lowre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> would haue intimated the ſame, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he delivered the ſaid letter miſſiue, &amp; not haue ſaid that he might haue charged them, if he would. Againe, it can be proved that from the firſt comming of the Laird of <hi>Lowreston</hi> and his ſervants into <hi>Abirdeen</hi> to eight hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res in the night, there were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually about the mercat croſſe, walking ſundrie honeſt men, who heard of no ſic matter. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, if the indorſement of the ſaid ſuppoſed charge were true, to wit, that it was execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before. 2. witneſſes, both ſervantes to the Laird of <hi>Lowreſton,</hi> betweene 7. and 8. houres at night, yet it was to no purpoſe.
<pb facs="tcp:13597:9"/> Becauſe it was not executed in the morning betweene eight and 12. houre at noone, before famous witneſſes according to an act of Parleament 1587.</p>
            <p>Vpon <hi>Thurſday</hi> and <hi>Friday</hi> following <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reaſon of the error of the Commiſſioners Letter aforeſaid, came to <hi>Abirdeen</hi> Mai. <hi>Iohn Welſh,</hi> Mai. <hi>Nathaniel Inglis,</hi> Ma. <hi>Iames Greig,</hi> Ma. <hi>Iohn ȝoung,</hi> Ma. <hi>Thomas Abirnethie,</hi> Ma. <hi>Archibald Symſon,</hi> Ma. <hi>Nathaniel Harlaw,</hi> M. <hi>Abraham Henderſon,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Roſſe:</hi> who fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Aſſembly diſſolved, and having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a ſubſcribed copie of the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings thereof, went to the place where the Aſſembly was holden, and for the diſcharge of their Commiſſion, tooke inſtruments vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the handes of two Notaries, that they were come to haue kept the ſaid Aſſembly and that they did ratifie all the proceedings thereof, in their own names, &amp; in the names of the Presbyteries who ſent them.</p>
            <p>After which proceedings, the 24. of <hi>Iuli,</hi> Mai. <hi>Iohn Forbes</hi> being in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſatisfie the Lords of Councell anent
<pb facs="tcp:13597:9"/> the alleadged diſobedience to his Maieſties charge, was ſend for by the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell to ſpeak with them who were convened, conſiſting of 6. Lords and 7. or 8. of the late Biſhops, &amp; Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſemblie (a noveltie not heard of before in Scotland) and was commanded to warde in the Caſtle of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> becauſe he would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the Aſſembly at <hi>Abirdeen</hi> by his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate iudgement, albeit he ſubmitted him ſelf and proceedings thereat to the General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie.</p>
            <p>Maiſter <hi>Iohn Welſh</hi> being alſo in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> was charged by a Meſſinger to compeir be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Councell the next day following; who compeiring &amp; refuſing to giue his oath, as he tooke it <hi>ſuper inquirendis,</hi> albeit he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it vpon the knowledge of the particular interrogatories, was likewiſe warded in the <hi>Tolbnith</hi> till eleaven houres, at which time both he and Mai. <hi>Iohn Forbes</hi> were tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Blacknes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> of <hi>August Ma. Robert Durie, Ma. Andro Duncan, Ma. Alexander Stranchen,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:13597:10"/> 
               <hi>Ma. Iohn Sharp,</hi> being ſummoned, compeired before the Councell, and with them M. <hi>Iohn Welſh,</hi> who was brought from <hi>Blacknes</hi> vpon his offer to giue his Oath vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pointes of his ſummonds, and were all committed to priſon in <hi>Blacknes,</hi> for the ſame cauſe for which <hi>Ma. Iohn Forbes</hi> was impriſoned.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third</hi> of <hi>October</hi> other 14. of thoſe, who had been either the 2. or 5. day of <hi>Iuly</hi> in <hi>Abirdeen,</hi> being cited before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell 7. of them, becauſe they doubted of the lawfulnes of the Aſſembly, til it were diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in a free Generall Aſſembly, were remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted home; and other 7. were warded for the ſame cauſe, for which the reſt were impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before. To wit, Mai. <hi>Charles Ferme,</hi> and <hi>Ma. Iohn Munro</hi> were warded in the Caſtle of <hi>Dorone,</hi> M. <hi>Nathaniel Inglis,</hi> &amp; M. <hi>Iames Greig,</hi> in the caſtle of <hi>Dumbertome, M. Iames Irving, Ma. William Forbes</hi> and <hi>Iohn Roſſe</hi> in the caſtle of <hi>Stirling.</hi> The reſt who were at <hi>Abirdeen</hi> the 2. and 5. of <hi>Iuly</hi> were not ſummoned, and ſo ſpared by the providence of God.</p>
            <p>After ſundrie Supplications, the ſaide 13.
<pb facs="tcp:13597:10"/> impriſoned Miniſters wrote reaſons to proove the Summonds fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſecret Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and proceedings before them to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to the authoriſed diſcipline of the Kirke, and contrarie to the laudable order obſerved in the Realme. And moſt humbly beſought their Lo: in the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who ſhall iudge the quick and the dead, to remit their cauſe and trial there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the Generall Aſſembly as only iudge competent thereto: as alſo to dimit them in peace that they might attende on their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. Which Supplications not regarded, they gaue to the Lords a Declinator ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by them al the ſaid 24. of <hi>October.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they did appeale, as it were, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the King and the Councell, to the K. and General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly: yet ſo that they did alwaies acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge themſelues bounde to ſubmit to the Councels iudgement, in any matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in any other ſubiect was bound to ſubmit. And howſoever they referred the anſwering of theticall Interrogatories to the Generall Aſſembly, yet to cleare themſelues of crimes
<pb facs="tcp:13597:11"/> obiected, they anſwered particular accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; hypotheticall interrogations in their Reſuming of the ſaid Summonds and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie to his Ma.</p>
            <p>Their Reaſons of declining the Councels iudgement contained in their laſt ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and pleaded when they gaue their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinator, be theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They alleadged and read an act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in anno 1592. whereby a former act of Parliament anno 1584. making it treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to decline the King &amp; Councels iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was interpreted, (for it paſſed whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the principall members both of Kirk and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth were forced to forſake the land, and it was neuer put in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate any thing to the priviledge that God hath given to the ſpirituall office-bearers in the Kirk concerning any eſſentiall cenſure having warrant of Gods word. But to iudge of the lawfulnes or vnlawfulnes of Synodes (wherof the General Aſſembly is the ſinew and life) is an eſſentiall cenſure, having war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Gods word.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:13597:11"/>2. By the practiſe of the Kirk ſince the act of Parliament 1584. recorded in the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Aſſembly, one Aſſembly hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer diſcerned and iudged another, and the proceedings thereof, as is evident in the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at <hi>Dundie</hi> anno 1597. which allowed the Aſſembly at <hi>Perth,</hi> &amp; the proceedings thereof; at both which Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies his Ma: was preſent: and (which is more) he required the queſtion made of the former to be decided by the later Aſſembly, as properly pertayning to that Iudicatorie. And in his Ma: Proclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> given to <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-Court</hi> 26. of <hi>September</hi> 1605. His Ma: not forgetting the practiſe of this Kirk, expecteth ſeparation of the ſuppoſed diſorders of the Aſſembly (for which we are called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) at the Aſſembly to be holden at <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi> the <hi>last Tweſday</hi> of <hi>Iuly</hi> next.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the Councell ſould take vpon them to iudge &amp; cenſure the lawfulnes or vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, the validitie or invaliditie of an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly: What were this, but to confounde Eccleſiaſticall, &amp; Civill Iudicatories, which
<pb facs="tcp:13597:12"/> hitherto haue been by law and practiſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely diſtinguiſhed? and which his Ma: in the Declaration of the ſaide Act of Parliament, anno 1584. profeſſeth to bee farre from his meaning. <hi>His intention being</hi> (as he there af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth) <hi>not in ſort to take away the lawfull and ordinarie iudgement in the Kirk, whereby Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and gude order might decay; But that as temporall Magistrates do iudge in temporall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo Spirituall Iuriſdiction ſould haue the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie triall in matters belonging to the Ministrie and their estate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, It may be affirmed, that it is no new thing to decline the Councell. For 1. there is a Declinator yet extant, ſubſcribed by the handes of thoſe ſame men of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, who are now moſt againſt vs, &amp; mo then 300. Paſtors: and 2. It is alſo, and hath been an ordinarie cuſtome in civill and cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall matters even of Civill perſons to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the Councell, and to take them to the iudgement of the Lords of Seſſion, or to the Iuſtice, vpon the different qualitie of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill fact.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13597:12"/>
            <p>At this time Ma. <hi>Robert ȝounſon,</hi> one of thoſe who had been remitted from <hi>Perth,</hi> becauſe he doubted of the lawfulnes of the Aſſembly, being mooved in conſcience, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned; and the ſame day and houre when theſe 13. were ſtanding before the Councel in that cauſe did compeir, and deſiring to be heard did acknowledge his ouerſight at <hi>Perth,</hi> and confeſſeth his trouble in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And therefore that albeit not ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by their Lo: yet charged by the living God, was compelled to come thether that day to iuſtifie that Aſſembly, &amp; whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings thereof, to the great aſtoniſhment of the Lords, and comfort of his brethren; who alſo ſubſcribed the Declinator with them. Who all thereafter were ſende backe to their ſeuerall priſons, &amp; Ma. <hi>Robert ȝoung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to the Caſtle of <hi>Stirling,</hi> with the other three that were warded there, and ſo as yet all continue in warde.</p>
            <p>In their Reſuming of Summondes and Apologie before mentioned, the Miniſters cleere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues of crimes obiected, by nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb facs="tcp:13597:13"/> of their proceedings alreadie repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and reaſons therein compriſed; and ȝet further by theſe Apologeticall anſwers.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the true cauſe of the lawfulnes of ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Synodes, and actions is the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Ieſus Chriſt, who as King of his Kirk, hath preſcribed and commaunded the ſame in his word, as is affirmed in the ſaide booke of Diſcipline, cap. 1. art. 10. So that the act of Parliament in anno 1592. is not the only warrant of ſic Synods and actions, being but the ciuill approbation of our chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Soveraigne mooved of chriſtian dutie, in teſtification of his ſubiection to Chriſt, &amp; willingnes to haue all his ſubiectes brought vnder humble obedience to the ſcepter of Chriſt, as may appeare by theſe wordes of the ſaid Act: <hi>And declareth the ſaid Aſſemblies Presbyteries, and Seſsions, Iuriſdiction and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipline thereof, to haue been in all times bigane, &amp; to be in all times comming, most gude, iust and godly in the ſelfe.</hi> Therfore, and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our ſubſcription and oath to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine the diſcipline of our Kirk conteined in
<pb facs="tcp:13597:13"/> the Confeſſion of our faith, we had highlie ſinned, if we had not forced the General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, being not forbidden to meet by the Councell, nor by the Kings Commiſſioner, no not by the Commiſſioners of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſemblie. For they only adviſed vs not to keepe the 5. day, and it was not kept. And ſeeing we had indangered the libertie of the Kirk, if we had not continued the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie to a certen day. For authoritie deſigned none, wherevnto we might haue conſented, and therefore, that day being expired, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could not bee appointed by the Kirke, according to the ordinance, and ordinarie cuſtome of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we did not tranſgreſſe the ſaid act of Parliament anno 1592. in any thing. 1. Becauſe it is no inſtituting law, but a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple approbation of Aſſemblies as they are appointed by the Kirk. 2. Becauſe the ſaid Approbation declares that it ſalbe lawful to the Kircke &amp; Miniſters euery ȝeere <hi>once,</hi> and ofter, as occaſion ſall require, to hold Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſemblies. 3. Becauſe in the ſame ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
<pb facs="tcp:13597:14"/> it is provided that the King, or his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner (if either be in the Towne where the general Aſſembly is held) be preſent, not to allow or diſallow the convening or hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſaid Aſſemblies, but only to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate the time &amp; place of the next Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. And therefore it is provided that the King or his Commiſſioner be preſent at Ilk Generall Aſſembly before the diſſolvinge thereof: Neither doth the proviſo giue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to the King or his Commiſſioner to nominate the time and place of the next Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly abſolutely, or by him ſelfe, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctly and with the Aſſembly. But if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King nor his Commiſſioner be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the place of the Aſſembly, then the proviſo ſaith expreſly, that it ſalbe leſum to the Aſſembly by them ſelues to nominate time and place of the next Aſſembly. But true it is, that his Ma: could not, and his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner would not be preſent, but (as ſaid is) voluntarily removed him ſelfe, while the Aſſemblie was continued to a certen time and place.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13597:14"/>
            <p>Thirdly, let it be ſuppoſed that it was an offence to hold, and to continue the ſaid Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie, ȝet it was not to be imputed vnto vs, becauſe we were but commiſſioners of ſundrie Presbyteries, wherevnto, &amp; not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in particular the ſaids letters from the Commiſſioners at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> were directed, which notwithſtanding, the Presbyteries ſend vs vnto the Aſſembly, &amp; approved our proceedings after the Aſſembly. So that the Presbyteries (if any) and not we are ſubiect to cenſure.</p>
            <p>All which allegations notwithſtanding, Ma. <hi>Iohn Forbes, Ma. Iohn Welſh, Ma. Robert Durie, Ma. Andrew Duncan, Ma. Iohn Sharp,</hi> and <hi>Ma. Alexander Stranchen</hi> were brought by the guard fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Blackenes</hi> to <hi>Linlitgow,</hi> there to be arraigned vpon <hi>Friday</hi> 10. <hi>Ianuary</hi> laſt, before the ſecret Councell of Treaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they declined the iudgement of the ſaid Councell, contrarie to the ſaide Act of Parleament anno 1584.</p>
            <p>The Councell firſt dealt with them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, to depart from their Declinator for
<pb facs="tcp:13597:15"/> his Ma: ſatisfaction. They were willing, ſo that all proceedings might be holden <hi>pro de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leto.</hi> Then the Councell willed them to take adviſe of their brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who were many then and there met together from many partes of <hi>Scotland.</hi> They did ſo, and at firſt found great difference of opinion. For ſome thought it lawfull, &amp; (in reſpect of inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>veniences likely to follow) verie expedient to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaid Declinator. In the end (with conſent) ſome of the Miniſters were ſend to the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, for eſchewing the preſent perill of their Brethren, to craue leaue for the priſoners to go, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferre with the Presbyteries (which ſend them in commiſſion) anent that moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without whoſe advice thei could do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the ſaid matter. This denied, it was thought by the whole number of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that the Priſoners could not paſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Declinator without great preiudice to the Kirk and Kingdome of Chriſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei were caried to the place of arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and named for their Prolocutors Ma. <hi>Thomas Craig, M. William Oliphant, M. Thomas
<pb facs="tcp:13597:15"/> Hope,</hi> &amp; <hi>M. Thomas Gray,</hi> who had all promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſpeake for them; but the two former being abſent were ſend for and refuſed to come. The other two by evident reaſons made the lawfulnes of the priſoners their proceedings, manifeſt to the conſciences of all. But the priſoners them ſelues ſo cleared themſelues &amp; their cauſe, that their enemies were aſtoniſhed, their doubtfull Brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, &amp; euery one that heard, ſatisfied. So that the Kings advocat was put to his ſhift, namely to charge the Aſſiſe only to finde, whether the priſoners had declined the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels iudgment or no, to which purpoſe only he gave them proofes. And the Aſſiſe was ſo troubled that they would haue been ridde of the matter. But that denied, &amp; they incloſed; at the firſt they all would haue clenſed the priſoners, which being ſignified to the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell they willed the Iuſtice clerk, and <hi>Henrie Steward</hi> Chancellor of the Aſſiſe (in <hi>England</hi> called the Forema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Iurie) to deale with the priſoners, to ſee, if ȝet they might be made to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor;
<pb facs="tcp:13597:16"/> which beeing refuſed, they were ſende back to the Aſſiſe to convict the priſoners in reſpect it was his Ma. wil, &amp; it behoued ſo to be, for preparing way to their peace. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it being voted 6. clenſed, and the reſt filed the Priſoners, to the vnſpeakeable grief and miſcontent of all men, except, &amp;c. But iudgement was ſuſpended till his Ma. mind be knowne.</p>
            <p>Whoſe minde (I hope) will be to reexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine matters, or to releaſe the priſoners, leſt otherwiſe he be guiltie of Innocent bloud; ȝea the bloud of the Lords holy ones (for ſuch are faithful Miniſters in a ſpecial ſenſe) which is right precious in his ſight. And therefore he ſaith, <hi>Touch not mine anoynted, &amp; do my Prophets no harme.</hi> And the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is inacted 11. Iacob. 6. ca. 91. That all Aſſiſes (or Iuries) be incloſed alone, and no perſon to be ſuffered to be with them, nor to repaire to them vnder any pretence whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, and that they bee not ſuffered to come out for whatſoeuer cauſe, till they being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, returne their anſwere to the iudge.
<pb facs="tcp:13597:16"/> Otherwiſe, or in caſe any point of the ſaide act be tranſgreſſed, the parties accuſed to be holden, and pronounced cleare &amp; innocent of the crimes and treaſons then laid to their charge. Nay though there were no ſuch ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, yet (I hope) his Ma: will take heed of ſuch innocent bloud, becauſe I haue expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of his naturall gratious diſpoſition. For howſoeuer incenſed by ſic as ſought themſelues, he made greeuous lawes againſt the Kirk in anno 1584. ȝea ſo, that hee put downe the Presbyteries and ſet vp Biſhops: ȝet vpon better information &amp; conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he put downe Papall Biſhops, and ſet vp the Presbyterie as the ordinance of God. Again, his Ma. being verie wiſe, can not but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rceyue how the titular Biſhops which he hath made, grieving that they haue a title without Iuriſdiction: And the late Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly, aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to that tranſcendent authoritie, which they ſee Commiſſioners Eccleſiaſticall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe in <hi>Englande,</hi> vnder pretence of his
<pb facs="tcp:13597:17"/> Ma: prerogatiue, vſe all the deviſes, friendes, and meanes they can, to incenſe his Ma: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Presbyteriall governement, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Generall Aſſembly, which holdeth all in aw.</p>
            <p>Beſeeching God to ſanctifie and bleſſe his Maieſtie, and his Royall Iſſue to iuſtifie wiſedome, and comfort his people. I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this Report to the Reader, and him to the grace of God. From my chamber the 21. of <hi>February</hi> 1606.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13597:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
